☆独家制作☆
喜马拉雅主播 & 微信公众号:
美国青少年英语
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
地球脉动 III
These people are hunting
这些人正在寻找
for one of the most endangered animals on the planet.
地球上最濒危的动物之一
The black rhino - an animal poached for its horn.
黑犀 一种因犀角而遭到偷猎的动物
But they aren't going to harm her.
但这些人并不会伤害它
Dumi Zwane and his team are on a rescue mission.
杜米·兹瓦内和他的团队正在执行救援任务
I don't think I'll ever stop fighting for rhino.
我永远不会放弃为犀牛而战的信念
It's just not possible.
这是我的使命
OK! Yeah...
好了
They're setting up a new breeding colony in a safe haven.
他们正在安全保护区建立一个新的繁殖群
Get her on two.
放在二号吊索上
Two. OK. That's good.
二号吊索 很好
This female is going to be at the very centre of it.
这只雌性黑犀将成为繁殖群的核心
She weighs over a tonne...
它重逾一吨
Go!
出发
..and there's only one way to get her out.
只有一种办法才能把它运走
That's it.
很好
There we are. Perfect!
就是这样 很好
When I watch it fly off, it's very emotional.
看着它这样飞走 我心情非常激动
It's a beautiful feeling.
是一种无与伦比的感觉
She is sedated and safe...
它被注射了镇静剂 很安全
...and in less than half an hour, she'll be back on the ground
半小时内便会返回地面
and starting a new life in a project that could save her entire species,
在这个可能拯救整个物种的项目中 开始属于它的新生活
thanks to Dumi and his remarkable team.
这一切都要感谢杜米和他的优秀团队
英雄
We started making the very first Planet Earth series
在20年前 我们开始制作
just over 20 years ago.
「地球脉动」系列
Since then, our camera teams have filmed all over the world
自那时起 我们的摄影团队走遍了世界各地
and visited some of its wildest and most remote corners.
调查了一些最原始 最偏僻的角落
But the truth is that most of the animals we filmed
然而事实上 我们拍摄的大多数动物
over these last two decades are now rarer than they were.
都在这20年间变得越来越稀少
And the places where they live
它们的生存家园
are in greater danger of destruction.
也面临着越来越大的危机
But I've seen another change in those years,
但这些年 我也看到了另一种变化
a hopeful change.
一种充满希望的变化
A new generation of remarkable people are stepping up
一代杰出的人们正在挺身而出
to save wildlife.
拯救野生动物
They're overcoming huge obstacles,
他们克服巨大障碍
travelling to dangerous places,
投身危险之境
and sometimes even risking their lives.
有时甚至冒着生命危险
To me, they are true heroes.
对我来说 他们是真正的英雄
This is the story of some of them.
本集将讲述这些英雄的故事
Hidden in the heart of the Andes
安第斯山脉深处
is the Centro Jambatu research centre.
隐藏着詹巴图研究中心
It's protecting members of what is, perhaps surprisingly,
它正在保护一些 也许会令人惊讶的
the most endangered group of animals in the world.
世界上最濒危的动物群体
Frogs.
青蛙
These individuals are the very last of their particular species.
它们是各自物种中 仅存的一些个体
They're brought here not only for protection,
它们被带到这里的目的 不只是保护它们
but, more importantly,
更重要的是
to increase their numbers.
让种群繁衍壮大
And the person to find them...
而找到它们的人是
..Jaime Culebras.
哈梅·库莱布拉斯
I was seven the first time that I saw a frog
我第一次见到青蛙时 只有7岁
and just changed my life.
那一刻改变了我的一生
And ever since his childhood,
自那之后
he's been exploring the remotest places
他一直在探索最偏远的地方
and searching for the rarest frogs.
寻找最稀有的青蛙
This is a leaf frog.
这是只叶蛙
He is just amazing.
它太奇妙了
It's impossible to don't fall in love with an animal like this, no?
看到这样的动物 怎么能不爱它呢
But there is one frog here that is very special.
这里有一只青蛙非常特别
His name, Sad Santiago.
名字叫做悲情圣地亚哥
This is Sad Santiago.
这是悲情圣地亚哥
He's sad because he's alone.
悲情是因为它非常孤单
He's one of the last members of his species.
它是物种中的最后一员之一
And he needs a female.
它需要一只雌性伴侣
Known as the Morona-Santiago harlequin frog,
莫罗纳-圣地亚哥丑角蛙
he may be the rarest frog in the world.
它可能是世界上最稀有的青蛙
While the other frogs here are doing their best
这里的其他青蛙都在尽可能
to increase their populations,
增加种群数量
Santiago has sat alone for four long years.
悲情圣地亚哥却孤零零等了四年
Maybe it's not the most beautiful frog, but he deserves love.
也许它不是最漂亮的青蛙 但也值得被爱
Santiago has now grown old,
悲情圣地亚哥已经老了
and if Jaime can't find a female for him soon,
如果哈梅不能尽快为它找到伴侣
the whole species could become extinct.
整个物种便可能就此灭绝
The last place where one of these frogs was seen...
这种青蛙最后的目击地点
..was high up on a mountain in the cloud forest of Ecuador.
是在厄瓜多尔云雾森林的高山上
There's only one way to get there.
路只有一条
Joining him is fellow frog-hunter Darwin
一同前往的还有青蛙猎人达尔文
and Jaime's partner and frog scientist, Francesca.
以及哈梅的伴侣 青蛙学家弗朗西斯卡
Oh!
哦
Come on, vamanos.
快点
Arriba.
上去
This is one of the wettest places on Earth,
这是地球上最潮湿的地方之一
and right now it's actually the wet season, the rainy season,
而且现在正是雨季
so it rains even more.
雨水更多
Soaking wet and teeming with bugs...
潮湿且到处都是虫子
..it's a perfect place for frogs.
这里是青蛙的理想家园
Let's go.
出发
Most frogs come out of hiding at night.
大多数青蛙夜晚才会现身
This place is extremely wonderful.
这个地方太奇妙了
But you have to be careful where you put your hands.
但需要时刻小心
Being with him is...
和他在一起
..it's unusual.
很特别
It's not your regular relationship.
这段关系很特别
Oh, he's obsessed. He's really obsessed.
他对青蛙非常着迷
Streams like this should be full of frogs
这样的溪流可能隐藏着许多
of many different species...
各种各样的青蛙
..but they search all night and find nothing.
但他们找了整夜 却一无所获
It's a silent forest.
整片森林鸦雀无声
It's sad.
很悲哀
The sound of frogs is slowly disappearing from our world.
青蛙的歌声 正渐渐消逝
The only place many frog species can now be found
如今 很多青蛙物种
is in a museum.
只能在博物馆中找到
A key reason is the spread of a fungus called chytrid...
一个关键原因 在于一种叫做壶菌的真菌的蔓延
..that can grow on the moist skins of frogs,
它能寄生在青蛙的湿润皮肤上
eventually killing them.
最终致其死亡
90 species are thought to have become extinct as a consequence,
据估计 90种青蛙因此而灭绝
and almost 600 more are now critically endangered.
还有近600种青蛙 正面临极高的灭绝风险
Before chytrid, I'm pretty sure that you could walk
如果没有壶菌 我敢保证
through the stream and see everywhere
这条小溪将到处都是
many, many, many frogs on the rocks,
趴在石头上的各种青蛙
calling "prrr-prrr"!
呱呱大叫
I wish I had been born before the frog disease.
我多希望我生活在壶菌病之前
Night after night...
夜复一夜
..they search the stream.
他们在小溪四处搜寻
Jaime!
哈梅
At last, there is a discovery.
终于 有了一个发现
The sound is a...
声音是
I don't know exactly where, but it's there, more or less.
我不确定具体在哪 但大概就在这里
En el agua!
在水里
We have it.
抓到了
A glass frog.
一只玻璃蛙
A really beautiful glass frog.
一只非常漂亮的玻璃蛙
Glass frogs are becoming increasingly rare,
玻璃蛙如今越来越稀少
and one day they, too, could disappear.
也许某一天便会彻底灭绝
But it's not what they are looking for.
但团队寻找的目标不是它
The fact is that countless species go extinct...
事实上 很多物种悄无声息地灭绝
..unnoticed.
鲜有人知
All Jaime can do is to continue his search
哈梅唯一能做的 便是继续寻找
for a mate for Santiago.
悲情圣地亚哥的伴侣
It's there?
在那里吗
I found a female!
我找到了一只雌性
Agh!
啊
Woohoo!
太棒了
It's a female! Look.
是只雌性 看啊
The size is bigger than the males.
体型比雄性大一些
Wow.
哇
I feel so happy!
我太高兴了
The first female!
第一只雌性
She could be the cornerstone of a new breeding programme.
这只雌蛙将成为新繁殖计划的关键
Santiago will be very, very, very, very, very happy.
悲情圣地亚哥彻底不悲情了
Because she's really beautiful!
这只雌蛙特别漂亮
In my hand, I have hope.
我手上拎着希望
I have the saviour of this species,
是这个物种的救星
for breeding programmes and for people to reproduce it.
也是繁殖计划的救星
I don't know, it's like I just have hope in my hand.
说不清 感觉希望就捧在我手上
There are over 7,000 species of frogs in the world,
世上有7000多种青蛙
and you may well ask...
可能会有人疑惑
..does it really matter if a few go extinct?
就算有几种消失了 又有什么大不了的
Well, just look at this tiny species
可是 看看这种小小的
of poison arrow frog.
箭毒蛙
Scientists discovered a chemical on its skin...
科学家发现它皮肤上的化学物质
..200 times stronger than morphine.
镇痛效果是吗啡的200倍
Now they are studying how it works to create powerful new painkillers.
如今科学家正在深入研究 以开发强效止痛药
But the natural world is not just one vast medicine chest.
但大自然远不只是一个药箱那么简单
It's far more than that.
它有着无可替代的重要性
It is our life support system,
大自然是我们的生命之源
the fabric that holds our world together.
是世界的基石
Remove a part of it, a species or a habitat,
如果我们失去了大自然的一部分
and there's no knowing what could happen.
将会造成未知的后果
A prime example is the forest elephant.
典型的例子 非洲森林象
They play a crucial role in maintaining
它们是非洲雨林的
the rainforests of Africa...
重要组成部分
..dispersing seeds and making clearings
它们帮助植物传播种子
that are then used by many other animals.
为其他动物创造生存空间
We filmed these images in 2004
2004年 我们为第一部「地球脉动」
for the first Planet Earth series.
拍摄了这些画面
Nine years later, poachers came here
九年后 偷猎者为了象牙
and killed 26 elephants for their ivory...
猎杀了26头森林象
..including four of the calves.
其中还有4只小象
Since that first series,
自那之后
the number of forest elephants across Africa
非洲森林象的数量
has dropped by two-thirds.
减少了三分之二
But stopping the slaughter is a risky business.
但阻止偷猎的工作十分危险
Abidjan, in Cote d'Ivoire, West Africa...
非洲西部 科特迪瓦 阿比让
..part of the global network in the illegal ivory trade.
是非法象牙交易的一个节点
A stranger has flown in from Vietnam,
一名女性来到此处
a hub for the import of ivory.
她来自象牙的重要进口国 越南
Elephant is my favourite animal on earth.
大象是我最爱的动物
Seeing how they are being killed
看到它们这样被猎杀
that just really upset me
真的很让我难过
and I just want to do something - anything I can.
我想做些力所能及的事情
Her name - Trang Nguyen.
她的名字是阮庄
Her speciality - infiltrating the illegal wildlife trade
她假装是象牙买家
by posing as a buyer.
打入非法野生动物交易内部
I have to change my character a bit
我得稍微改变一下性格
because normally I'm very chatty
因为通常我很健谈
and I like to smile, and I like to talk to people
喜欢笑 喜欢与人交谈
but I have to be cold, and I have to be mean.
但我必须变得冷漠刻薄
When you're going in, you're dealing with criminals.
你身边都是罪犯
You're telling lies.
依靠谎话
You have to pretend to be someone else.
假装自己是一个买家
If by accident you blow that cover
如果不小心露馅了
it's possible that I'll be killed.
很可能就没命了
Trang is working with a network of conservationists called EAGLE.
阮庄和一个叫EAGLE的保护组织合作
Her contact here is Rens Ilgen.
她的联络人是伦斯·伊尔根
But what is particular with this new trade in West Africa is,
这里的象牙交易有个特点
as you can see, a lot of the tusks are from baby elephants.
很多象牙都是小象的
So, they're really down to the last elephants.
这说明 幸存的大象已经所剩无几了
Last week, seven people were killed.
上周 有七个人被杀
Seven ranger was killed?
七个护林员被杀吗
So, clearly, it is not just about the ivory trade,
所以显然 如今已经不仅是象牙交易的问题
but a lot of people, rangers, that are being killed as well.
还有很多无辜的人 为了保护大象而失去生命
It's...it's war. It's war.
-简直是一场战争 -一场战争
And they're even going for the baby elephants.  Yeah.
-连刚出生的小象也不放过 -是啊
Now Trang is set her task.
现在阮庄确定了自己的任务
So, I want you to meet the godfather of ivory.
我希望你去见见象牙交易的首领
We already arrested him four years ago
四年前 他因藏有400公斤象牙
when he had 400kg of ivory,
而被逮捕过一次
which he was supplying to the Vietnamese community
那些象牙是提供给越南的
linked to the Vietnamese mafia.
与当地黑帮有所牵连
As he has been arrested before, he might be very cautious.
因为被抓过 所以他可能会很谨慎
It might be dangerous.
任务可能会很危险
She prepares her disguise as a businesswoman -
她打扮成一名商人
but under her jacket,
但衣服下
hidden recording equipment.
藏有录音设备
EAGLE's undercover agents have been following
保护组织已经秘密跟踪
the godfather for years.
象牙组织首领好几年了
Now is the moment to catch him.
现在是时候将他绳之以法了
This is your first meeting.
这是第一次会面
You're just going to discuss and get to know each other.
只是聊聊天 互相了解一下
See if they have the products. Exactly.
-看看他们有没有货 -没错
I'm going in,
我进去后
and I need to sit facing away from the door,
要背对门坐着
because I don't want people to see me with him.
因为不能让别人看见我在这里
We will be close by...  Yep.
-我们就在附近 -好的
..and nothing will go wrong.
一定会很顺利的
OK.
好的
Good luck.
祝你好运
Bye.
再见
She meets the godfather at a local cafe.
她在一个当地的咖啡馆与组织首领会面
Good evening.
晚上好
The secret cameras capture the story.
秘密摄像机拍下了一切
Nice to meet you.
很高兴见到你
I've heard a lot about you.
久仰大名
I'm looking for opportunities
我正在寻找
to start working and doing business over here.
在这里做生意的机会
So you need someone to help you in your business?
你在找合作伙伴
So they want to know exactly what you need from us.
他们想知道你到底需要什么
Need?
我的需要
Yes.
是的
I heard that you have some interesting products
我听说你们有一些有意思的货
that i want.
是我想要的
Right?
对吗
What is she talking about?
她在说什么
As what?
具体是什么
As elephant ivory.
象牙
But the godfather denies having any ivory for sale.
然而组织首领矢口否认
We can't do ivory because we only work in wood.
我们只做木材 不做象牙交易
So we can get it here
我们能搞到
but now, no.
但现在不行
For the time being
目前来说
it's not possible.
是不可能的
Merci.
谢谢
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
是的
Merci.
谢谢
Perhaps there's no ivory.
也许他真的没有象牙
Or maybe he doesn't trust Trang.
或者也许他不信任阮庄
It's a serious setback.
这是个巨大的挫折
But there are other traders out there.
但还有其他象牙贩子
Perhaps her presence in town will draw them in.
阮庄的出现也许会引起他们的注意
Every day that passes,
每过一天
more elephants are killed.
就有更多的大象被杀害
For Trang, this work is very personal.
对于阮庄来说 这份工作和她的生命有关
When I was 23, I got the phone call.
我23岁时 接到了一通电话
The doctor told me that I had bowel cancer.
医生告诉我 我患有结肠癌
The first thing pop up in my mind is that I'm so young,
我当时第一个念头是 我还这么年轻
well, how can I get cancer?
怎么会得癌症呢
Once you have cancer,
一旦患上癌症
you don't know how long you're going to live for,
就不知道自己还能活多久
and if I want to do anything, then I should just do it now.
如果有什么想做的事情 就趁现在去做吧
And that's when I said, "OK, I'm just going to do undercover,"
因此我决定去做卧底
because I don't know when I'm going to die.
因为我不知道自己什么时候会死
I might as well do something really meaningful.
我想做一些有意义的事情
Currently, Trang is in remission.
目前 阮庄的病情得到了缓解
Three days later, there's a breakthrough.
三天后 事情有了突破
A video sent by a trader.
一个卖家发来了视频
I can see that this video have about 14, 15 ivory.
视频里大约有14 15根象牙
They are big tusks, they are also small tusks as well.
有大有小
It's obviously come from baby elephants.
毫无疑问是从小象身上割下来的
The bait has been taken.
卖家上钩了
Trang and the EAGLE team must act fast.
阮庄以及EAGLE团队必须迅速采取行动
She goes to meet the new targets.
她前去与新目标会面
First job...
首先
Bonsoir.
晚上好
..gain their trust.
要取得他们的信任
Cheers.
干杯
Cheers.  Cheers.
We have a hotel room.
我们有一间房
Let us go there.
可以去那里
We need to weigh how much the items are
给货物称重
and then we just give the money
一手交钱 一手交货
He goes his way, I go my way.
各取所需
Done.
成交
Eventually, Trang persuades the traders to move to
最后 阮庄说服卖家来到
a hotel room nearby...
附近的一家酒店
..to weigh the ivory and make the transaction.
给象牙称重 完成交易
Close the door. Close the door.
关上门
It's good.
品相很好
Ivory is sold by the kilo.
象牙按重量计价
That is just over 20.
这些有20多公斤
20.2?
20.2
20.3.
20.3
A whole elephant family was killed for this haul.
整个大象家族因此而被杀
It's worth over £5,000.
价值超过5000英镑
Here, that is a year's salary.
在这里 这相当于一整年的收入
What the traders don't realise...
然而卖家并不知道
..is that the police are in the room above,
警察就在楼上待命
waiting for a text from Trang.
等待阮庄的消息
OK, let's go.
行动
Who's there?
是谁
It's reception.
客房服务
Service?
Who is it?
是谁
It's reception.
客房服务
Okay, just a minute please.
好的 等一下
You go open the door.
你去开门
OK.
好
Just put it down here.
就放这里
Police! Police!
警察 警察
Don't move, don't move, don't move!
不许动 不许动
Lie down!
趴下
Don't move!
不许动
Hands behind your back!
手放在背后
I don't know, I don't know, I don't know!
我什么都不知道
What's this?
这是什么
I don't know!
我不知道
For her own safety,
为了保护阮庄的安全
she has to keep her cover story and behave as a criminal...
她必须继续装作犯罪分子
..which means she must also be arrested.
因此她也必须被逮捕
Shut up!
闭嘴
A link in the global supply chain...
象牙全球供应链的一个节点
..broken.
被切断了
Trang is whisked away,
阮庄被迅速带走
whilst the traders are taken to the police station,
而卖家则被送到警察局
none the wiser about her involvement.
对她的卧底身份毫不知情
Over the next year, EAGLE catch 140 more traffickers
在接下来的一年 EAGLE在打击全球野生动物贸易的斗争中
in the fight against the global wildlife trade.
抓获了140多名非法交易人员
But for Trang, this is her last operation.
但对于阮庄来说 这是她的最后一次行动
It's why we can show her face.
因此我们能够拍摄她的面孔
I have been doing undercover work
我从事卧底工作
and sting operations for quite a while
参与诱捕行动有一段时间了
and it can be really stressful.
压力确实很大
It's not safe for her to stay a minute longer than necessary.
她不能再逗留在这里了
Trang's final task is to vanish from Abidjan...
阮庄的最后一项任务 就是从阿比让
..for ever.
彻底消失
Across the world, the numbers of wild animals are falling alarmingly.
世界各地 野生动物的数量正以惊人的速度减少
In just two decades -
短短二十年里
since we started making the first Planet Earth series -
也就是自从第一部「地球脉动」
the abundance of wildlife around the globe has dropped,
全球野生动物的数量
on average, by over 30%.
平均下降了超过30%
We're facing a disaster, a catastrophe.
我们正面临一场灾难 一场浩劫
Scientists say that we're on the edge of a mass extinction.
科学家认为 我们正处在物种大灭绝的边缘
It's being caused by human activity.
而这正是人类活动造成的
So humans also have the power to stop it.
因此 人类也有能力阻止这一切
It takes many qualities to save even one species.
拯救物种的艰巨任务 需要很多品质
Determination...
决心
..courage...
勇气
..and passion.
以及热情
And often, there's another ingredient that's needed...
同时 往往还需要一种品质
..the ability to think big.
放眼未来 敢于创新
In Vienna, Katharina Huchler is just starting a new job.
在维也纳 凯瑟琳娜·赫切勒开始了一份新工作
The pay is terrible.
工资很低
The hours are long.
工作时间很长
And there are no days off.
而且没有休息日
She is about to become a foster mother.
她将成为一名寄养母亲
Hi.
嗨
Good morning.
早上好
Hi. Hi.
嗨
And these are her new babies...
这些是她的新宝宝
You're pretty awake. Hi.
你好有精神 嗨
..28 of one of the world's rarest birds.
28只世界上最稀有的鸟类之一
Hey. Hi.
嘿 你好
The northern bald ibis.
隐鹮
You really quickly fall in love with them.
你会很快爱上它们的
They were hunted to extinction in Europe over 400 years ago.
400多年前在欧洲 隐鹮被猎杀殆尽
These chicks were born in a zoo.
这些雏鸟是在动物园出生的
Katharina's task is to teach them
凯瑟琳娜的任务 是教它们
to become wild, free birds.
如何在野外生存 自由飞翔
Yes, yes, yes. Komm. Komm.
来吧来吧
To do that, she must convince them that she is their mother.
为此 她必须让雏鸟相信 自己是它们的母亲
It's a process called imprinting.
这是一个叫做印随的过程
While it's happening, the chicks must never see or hear
这期间 不能让雏鸟看到或听到
any other human except Helena,
除了海伦娜的任何人或者声音
who's an ibis foster mum for the second time.
海伦娜是第二次成为隐鹮的寄养母亲
They must always wear identical yellow clothes
她们必须穿着完全相同的黄色服装
and repeat the same noises again and again.
并且不停发出相同的声音
We mimic the sounds the adults make, it's like...
我们模仿成年隐鹮的声音 像是
But I'm not good yet at doing it!
我的模仿还不够好
Goodnight.
晚安
They're here when the chicks fall asleep...
她们陪着雏鸟直到睡着
Sleep well.
做个好梦
..and the first thing they see when they awake.
雏鸟醒来一睁眼看到的也是她们
Good morning, waldies! Hallo!
早上好
Let's have something to eat, shall we? Yes, let's eat.
去吃点早饭吧 好不好
They're a bit like every human baby.
它们有点像人类宝宝
They just need their food bit by bit by bit
它们需要一天从早到晚
all day long.
一口一口吃饭
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
很好很好
Oh, no, we did it all wrong!
糟了 出错了
It's really like changing the nappies of the babies.
就跟给宝宝换尿布一样
28 mouths to feed and bottoms to wipe,
负责28只雏鸟的吃喝拉撒
and all the time talking to the birds.
还要不断跟雏鸟交流
Komm, komm, waldies! Komm, komm!
来吧来吧
Feeling really tired.
感觉很累
Yeah, I'd really like to sleep a little bit more.
想多睡一会儿
As the weeks pass, the bond grows.
随着时间的流逝 他们的感情越来越深
And then it is time for their next stage
接下来 雏鸟要进入
in becoming wild birds.
成为野生隐鹮的新阶段
They move to a field in the Austrian Alps.
他们来到奥地利阿尔卑斯山的一片草地上
They've now grown their adult flight feathers...
雏鸟已经长出了可以飞行的羽毛
...but they're still chicks on the inside.
但它们内心还只是雏鸟
So the imprinting must continue.
因此 印随工作还要继续
With this hand gesture we do,
我们用这个手势
we imitate the bill of an adult ibis
模仿成年隐鹮的喙
and we combine it with the greeting sound.
并配合隐鹮的叫声
So, this is...
像这样
All this imprinting is for a very important reason.
这样的模仿是出于一个重要的原因
These are migratory birds.
隐鹮是候鸟
In autumn, they must fly south
秋季 它们必须飞往南方
to their warm feeding grounds in Italy.
飞往位于意大利的温暖觅食地
And that is a problem.
而这是个问题
They know that they need to go somewhere,
它们知道自己必须去往某个地方
but they don't know in which direction and how far.
但不知道往哪个方向飞 要飞多远
So they need to learn the route from their parents.
它们需要从父母那里学习迁徙路线
Their human mothers must show them the way.
现在这成了寄养母亲的工作
And that requires a little ingenuity.
而这需要一点创意
This is where the imprinting is put to the test.
是时候检验印随的效果了
Will the birds follow them...
如果她们坐在一架飞机上
..even in a microlight?
隐鹮会跟着她们吗
Komm, komm!
来吧来吧
Komm, komm, waldies!
来吧来吧鸟儿们
Komm, komm!
来吧来吧
Come come, ibis! Come, come!
来吧来吧鸟儿们
Getting too close is dangerous for both birds and humans.
过近的距离对于隐鹮和人都很危险
There's a bird in the lines!
有只鸟飞在绳索间
The others are all at the front.
其他都飞在前面
There's one near the lines.
有只鸟飞得太近了
Close to the lines on the left.
靠近左侧的绳索
It's all fine.
没问题了
After a wobbly start...
尽管开头不太顺利
..at last they settle.
但最终隐鹮老实了下来
Let's go!
出发
The imprinting has worked.
印随工作大成功
Our birds did very well today.
隐鹮今天表现非常好
But their biggest challenge is still to come.
但最大的挑战还在后面
The Zillertal Alps.
齐勒塔尔阿尔卑斯山脉
A great wall of rock and ice.
岩石和冰雪组成巨大的一堵墙
It's going to be the most important flight
这将是隐鹮生命中
of their young lives.
最重要的一次飞行
It will take them to the very edge of exhaustion.
这将会让它们精疲力竭
A lot of young birds die during their first migration.
很多年轻的鸟在第一次迁徙时 失去了性命
They are still so inexperienced.
它们过于缺乏经验
There's also danger for the foster mothers and the pilots.
这对于寄养母亲和飞行员来说同样危险
If there is a problem with the microlights,
如果飞机出了问题
there is no safe place to land.
根本没有安全的地方着陆
To gain enough height to fly over these mountains...
要想飞越这些山峰
..they must find columns of rising air called thermals.
它们必须找到叫做热气流的上升气流
A skill these birds would normally learn
这种技术往往需要鸟儿
by following their natural mothers.
在跟随父母迁徙时习得
It takes expert piloting to find the thermals.
找到上升气流 需要精湛的飞行技术
Once within one,
而上升气流中
it's turbulent and unpredictable.
气流猛烈 难以控制
We're very high now.
高度很高了
With every turn, the mothers must make sure
每次转弯 她们都要确认
all 28 birds are following.
28只隐鹮是否都跟上了
One's separate from the others.
有一只脱离大部队了
All 28 birds here.
28只隐鹮都在
At last, they make it over the highest ridge.
最终 它们飞过了最高的山峰
From now on, it should be easy flying.
从此以后 飞行就轻松多了
What we are trying to do, apart from saving the ibis,
我们的目的 不仅是拯救隐鹮
is trying to give hope to people.
还是给人们带来希望
If you can bring back one species,
如果你可以让一个物种重获新生
you can also do it with others.
其他物种自然同样可以
A species once left for dead now has a future.
曾经濒临灭绝的物种 如今再度振翅高飞
And they head for their safe winter home
它们飞向自然保护区
in a protected nature reserve.
那里将成为它们安全的冬季家园
But as we have seen throughout this series,
但正如在这个系列中看到的
many species are losing the wild habitats they need to survive.
许多物种正在失去它们赖以生存的野生栖息地
It's the biggest cause of extinction.
而这正是导致灭绝的最大原因
Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Amazon rainforest.
这一点在亚马逊雨林中最为明显
Our Planet Earth crews have filmed here many times
二十年里 「地球脉动」摄制组
over the last two decades.
多次在这里拍摄
And in that time, over 16,000 million trees...
而这段时间里 超过160亿颗树
..have been felled.
遭到砍伐
To safeguard the countless species that live here...
为了保护生活在此的无数物种
..the forest itself must be protected..
雨林本身必须得到保护
And there's a force rising up to do just that.
而有一股力量 正为此而崛起
Look at this ant, Bella
瞧这只蚂蚁 贝拉
This ant is all alone.
孤零零一只蚂蚁
It's helpless.
脆弱无助
But when they are all together
但蚂蚁群团结一心
they are strong.
便攻无不克
Alessandra Korap is one of the leaders of the Munduruku.
亚历珊德拉·科拉普是蒙杜鲁库族的领袖之一
They have been the guardians of this part of the Amazon
他们是这部分亚马逊的守护者
for thousands of years.
有着数千年的历史
We, the Munduruku
我们蒙杜鲁库族人
we are part of this forest
是这片森林的一部分
and we must keep being like this little ant.
我们必须像蚂蚁一样团结一心
We have to keep bothering people.
对抗破坏森林的人
I love this forest!
我爱这片森林
It's a market, it's a pharmacy.
既是市场 又是药房
But the forest is not just there for the Munduruku.
但这片森林不仅仅只属于蒙杜鲁库族
It's there for the planet.
而是属于整个地球
When she was a child, this part of the Amazon forest
亚历珊德拉小时候 这片亚马逊森林
stretched unbroken for hundreds of miles.
是一望无际的处女地
Now it's being carved up...
但如今它被割成碎片
..for mining, for timber,
为了矿产与木材
but most of all for agriculture.
而最主要的是为了农业
This is the front line in the battle for the Amazon,
这里是亚马逊保卫战的前线
and it is a deadly one.
这场战争沾满了血泪
In the last decade, more than 300 people have been murdered
过去的十年里 巴西有超过300人
in Brazil defending the environment.
为保护环境而死
When you protect a forest
保护森林时
our lives are at stake.
总是会面临生命危险
I could be killed at any moment.
我随时可能失去生命
They tried to kill me twice
他们两次试图杀死我
They tried to kill other leaders
试图杀害其他部落领袖
by burning them alive, inside their house.
被关在屋子里 活活烧死
The Munduruku, like many indigenous groups,
像许多原住民群体一样
live in isolated communities
蒙杜鲁库族与世隔绝
vulnerable to attack from miners, farmers and loggers.
经常遭到开采 农业和伐木等活动的侵扰
The loggers are coming in.
伐木工人来到这里
They always go around with their gunmen.
总是拿着枪走来走去
A lot of people don't know what's happening
很多部落里的人
here in the territory.
不知道发生了什么
So they think it's a lie, that we're making it up.
因此他们以为这是我们编造出来的谎言
Why do they have to cut down so much?
为什么要砍这么多树呢
The Amazon's future is decided 2,000 miles away.
亚马逊的未来 是由远在3200公里外的巴西政府决定的
Here, in the parliament of Brazil,
在这里 议员正在讨论
new laws are being debated to allow the exploitation
制定新的法案 允许对原住民土地
of their traditional tribal land.
进行商业开发
But Alessandra has a plan -
但亚历珊德拉不甘于此
to unite with other tribes
她计划联合其他部落
and organise a protest so big
发起一场规模空前的抗议
that it cannot be ignored.
让政府听到他们的声音
We need to prepare ourselves
我们需要做好准备
to go to the city.
前往城市
When we leave our home
当我们离开家园
to go to Brasilia
前往首都巴西利亚时
we find many enemies.
我们发现了许多敌人
And the ones who wear suits
西装革履的人
are making war, making laws.
正在制造战争 制定法律
Before we used to use arrows
我们曾经用弓箭
to fight for our territory.
保卫我们的领地
Today is different.
如今一切都不一样了
It's a three-day journey to the capital city.
这趟前往首都的旅程 将花费三天
Trucks rumble to and from the fields...
曾经雨林覆盖的土地
..land that used to be rainforest.
如今变成了农田
They're carrying thousands of tonnes of soya beans.
隆隆的卡车装满了大豆
It's shipped from the heart of the Amazon across the world.
从亚马逊深处运往世界各地
Not to feed humans...
这些大豆不是用来养活人类
..but to feed livestock.
而是用来喂养家畜
Our forest,
我们的森林
our Amazon,
我们的亚马逊
is being destroyed
遭到严重破坏
for you to have your chicken farm, your pig farm.
就只是为了养鸡 养猪
Eventually, Alessandra makes it to Brasilia.
最终 亚历珊德拉抵达了巴西利亚
News of the protest has spread all over the country.
她的抗议行动引起了全国的关注
200 groups have united in a huge camp.
有200个不同的部落加入了她的行列
From the northeast of Brazil - the Xukuru.
有来自巴西东北部的苏库鲁人
From the southern edge of the Amazon - the Karaja.
有来自亚马逊南部的卡拉加人
If we decide now to agree to the approval of this law
如果我们同意这项法案
then we are agreeing to the deaths of our children.
就等于将我们的子孙后代置之死地
For ten days, they protest against the proposed laws.
抗议活动持续了十天
I see us as little ants, fighting against the machine.
我觉得我们就像小蚂蚁 与国家机器斗争
But when we get together
但当我们团结起来
then we start to bother them.
他们就不得不重视
Then they feel it, then they hear it.
就会听见我们的声音 感受到我们的力量
Alessandra and the other leaders have created
亚历珊德拉和其他部落领袖
the biggest protest by indigenous people ever held in Brazil.
掀起了巴西历史上 最大的原住民抗议活动
Later, one of the proposed laws was withdrawn.
最终努力没有白费 其中一项法案被推翻了
A small but significant victory
这是亚历珊德拉为保护巴西自然资源
in Alessandra's fight for Brazil's wild places.
取得的一个虽小 却意义重大的胜利
The destruction of habitats is currently the biggest threat
目前 野生动物面临的最大危机
to the survival of animal species.
是栖息地的丧失
But there is an even greater disaster on the horizon.
然而 更大的危机正在逼近
Our climate is changing.
那就是气候变化
Seasons have become unpredictable and more extreme.
季节变得越来越不稳定且极端
Our planet is getting hotter.
地球正在变暖
Scientists predict that if the global temperature
科学家预测 如果全球气温上升
rises by over two degrees,
超过2摄氏度
it is likely to become the number one cause of extinction.
那么气候变化就可能成为 导致物种灭绝的最主要原因
To halt climate change,
要阻止气候变化
perhaps politicians need to become heroes, too.
也许需要政客们自身也成为英雄
Hello, good evening, and a warm welcome to Glasgow
大家晚上好 欢迎来到格拉斯哥
and the start of the long-awaited climate summit, COP26.
参加这场期待已久的气候峰会 COP26的开幕
World leaders, prominent scientists
各国领导人 杰出的科学家
and advisers all ready for 12 days of...
都已做好准备
Mohamed Nasheed is a politician,
默罕默德·纳希德是一名政治家
the former president of the Maldives.
曾担任马尔代夫的总统
The doctors said that they took 16 ball bearings
医生说 他们从我身上
from all parts of my body.
取出了16颗钢珠
I was unconscious for two days.
我昏迷了两天
Over his political career, he has been tortured, imprisoned
他的政治生涯充满艰辛 经受过酷刑 牢狱之灾
and recently survived an assassination attempt.
并且刚刚在刺杀下逃过一劫
But during that time,
但这期间
he's also fought relentlessly against climate change.
他也一直在为应对气候变化而奋斗
..pleasure to be able to bring you Mohamed Nasheed.
很荣幸邀请默罕默德·纳希德
In Glasgow, on the eve of climate conference COP26,
在格拉斯哥气候峰会COP26的前一天
he is addressing a rally.
他在一个集会上发表了演讲
Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
So, we come to COP26
我们来到COP26
to find out whether we still have a future.
是为了探索人类的未来
If we cannot have a legally binding agreement
如果我们不能签署一个有法律效力的协议
not to push global temperatures
阻止全球气温升高
above 1.5 degrees,
超过1.5度
my country will be gone,
我的祖国就将彻底消失
as will all the world's coral reefs
世界上所有珊瑚礁和大部分雨林
and most of the rainforests.
也会随之消亡
Is all this devastation really worth it,
仅仅为了能在短短几年内
so that we can continue to burn coal and fossil fuel
继续燃烧煤炭以及化石燃料
for a few more years?
而引发如此灾难 真的值得吗
I have spent a lifetime
我一生
fighting for my country,
都在为我的国家而战
and with more determination than ever,
而且我现在比以往任何时候都更有决心
because I know my time on Earth might be cut short.
因为我清楚 我生活在这颗美丽星球上的时间可能已经不多了
Mohamed Nasheed's passion for the natural world
默罕默德·纳希德对大自然的热爱
began the first time he saw a coral reef.
始于他第一次见到珊瑚礁
My earliest memory
我最早的记忆
is with the ocean and the reef.
就是与海洋和珊瑚礁在一起
We were the first generation to actually see the reef.
我们是第一代真正见到珊瑚礁的人
Masks and goggles came to the Maldives
潜水面罩和护目镜在60年代末
in the late '60s, early '70s.
70年代初出现在马尔代夫
Once we started seeing the reef as a living creature...
一旦把珊瑚礁看作一个活着的生物
..we were just dumbfounded.
我们就会惊叹不已
But Nasheed's beloved coral is now the habitat
然而纳希德深爱的珊瑚礁
that is most threatened by climate change.
如今是受气候变化威胁最大的栖息地
The critical tipping point is a 1.5 degree temperature rise.
温度上升的临界值是1.5度
Beyond that, most reefs will die,
一旦高过这个数字 大多数珊瑚礁将死亡
leaving nothing but rubble.
留下一片废墟
When you think of a bigger picture,
当你把目光放的长远
then your own life is not so important.
自己一个人的生命便不再那么重要了
It's what you want to get done which is important.
重要的是能在生命中做些什么
Nasheed's aim is to persuade politicians to cut the use
纳希德的目标 是说服政治家减少使用
of coal and other fossil fuels.
煤炭和其他化石燃料
He repeats this plea at every climate conference.
他在每个气候会议上 都重复着这份诉求
You need to be able to convince people,
你必须说服人们
try to educate people.
引导人们
We are in trouble.
我们处于危机之中
We will not survive if the planet is heated above 1.5 degrees.
如果地球气温升高超过1.5度 人类将无法生存
We must act now.
我们必须立刻采取行动
At first, journalists are reporting on some eye-catching promises
一开始 有些国家领导人
made by heads of state.
做出了引人注目的承诺
18 countries have committed themselves
18个国家承诺
to a plan to stop using coal-fired power plants.
制定一个停止使用燃煤发电厂的计划
It is an election issue now.
如今这是一个关乎选举的问题
That is why world leaders have joined the rhetoric.
因此国家领导人才会做出这样的承诺
The next stage - turning promises into solid plans.
下一阶段 将承诺落实为具体计划
And Nasheed is busy working behind the scenes.
纳希德正在幕后努力推动这些计划
If they don't agree, we will ring their ministers, their presidents
如果他们不同意 我们就给总统以及部长打电话
and get them online.
在线上谈判
I think that's what we're trying to do.
这就是我们要做的事情
So let's do this.
立刻行动吧
How are you, Prime Minister?
你好 总理
Yeah, OK.  I can hear you,
我听得很清楚
but I can hear the Prime Minister much clearer.
但我听总理的声音更清楚
All countries need to agree to the final text -
所有国家都要签署最终的协议
and some won't.
但有些国家拒绝了
People who want to continue fossil fuel,
坚持使用化石燃料的人
I think, are the bad guys.
我认为 是坏人
And people who want to change, I feel, are the good guys.
而那些愿意做出改变的人 我则认为是好人
Thank you. Thank you so much.
谢谢 非常感谢
After 14 days, this COP closes...
14天后 COP26闭幕
..with some progress,
虽然取得了一些进展
but also with big compromises.
但也有许多妥协
An agreement was finally reached this evening
一份协议中关于煤炭使用的关键部分
after a key section on the future use of coal
在最后一刻被加以修改 放宽标准
was at the last moment watered down.
才终于得到通过
Without urgent new commitments,
关键的新提案被搁置
the target of 1.5 degrees will be missed.
1.5度的目标将无法实现
It is disastrous.
简直是灾难
It will...
这将
If you picture this, if you can fathom it...
想象一下 如果你能理解这一切
..the coral will bleach
珊瑚礁将白化
and they will die,
最终死去
and when they are dead,
而当珊瑚礁死亡
the fish and the marine life that lives there...
其中的鱼类以及海洋生命
..cease to exist.
也将不复存在
You would have thought that your normal prime minister
你本以为你的总理
and president...
和总统
..would have a better grip on understanding things.
能更好的理解这一切的重要性
And not just go on and on and on
而不是一味地坚持
about protecting their way of life.
维护自己的生活方式
So it's frustrating to see politicians...
所以看到那些政客如此无知
..who doesn't seem to understand it.
真的很让人沮丧
With current policies,
根据现行的政策
99% of coral reefs could be gone...
99%的珊瑚礁将在30年内
..in under 30 years.
彻底消失
Other habitats will follow.
其他的生态系统也将随之衰败
You can't lose hope.
不能因此失去希望
You cannot give up.
也不能因此而放弃
I will not stop.
我不会停下脚步
Nasheed believes there is a solution.
纳希德相信存在一个解决方案
The more environment becomes an election issue,
随着环境问题逐渐成为选举的重点
there will be more action on climate.
会有越来越多领导人采取行动应对气候变化
Every time you vote, in every election,
请把你手中每一张选票
please tick the planet.
都投给我们美丽的地球
The challenge of saving species can't be left to a few
拯救物种的艰巨任务不能只靠
heroic individuals working against the odds.
在逆境中奋斗的少数英雄人物
It's those in positions of great power
拥有更大权力的人
who can make the most difference.
才能做出更大的改变
So, ultimately, it is they who must take the most responsibility.
因此 最终他们必须担起最大的责任
Perhaps one of our roles is to hold them to account.
也许我们的职责之一 便是向他们问责
Time is running out for many species,
对于很多物种来说 时间已所剩无几
but I truly believe that if the right decisions are made now,
但我真心相信 如果现在在这个关键时刻
at this critical moment,
能做出正确的决定
there could still be a bright future for all life
所有生命仍有一个光明的未来
on our wonderful planet Earth.
在我们美丽的地球上生生不息 脉动不止
自本纪录片拍摄以来
悲情圣地亚哥辞世
但它的物种群落日益壮大
六十只隐鹮振翅 踏上了迁徙的征程
纳希德坚持在气候峰会上不断提出诉求
阮庄投身于新一代卧底警探的培养工作
二十头黑犀被运至安全的家园
在巴西 六个原住民土地
如今依法受到保护
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Explore this free interactive, and make origami animals.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
and follow the links to the Open University.
点击链接进入开放大学
Or to order a free printed version,
或者订购免费印刷版
visit the website or call the numbers on the screen.
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码